export const ch1 = [
  {
    mcq: [
      {
        numb: 1,
        question:
          "Which of the following is an example of simple harmonic motion?",
        answer: "the motion of simple pendulum",
        options: [
          " the motion of simple pendulum",
          " the motion of ceiling fan",
          " the spinning of the Earth on its axis",
          "a bouncing ball on a floor",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 2,
        question:
          "If the mass of the bob of a pendulum is increased by a factor of 3, the period of the pendulum's motion will",
        answer: "remain the same ",
        options: [
          "be increased by a factor of 2 ",
          " remain the same ",
          " be decreased by a factor of 2 ",
          " be decreased by a factor of 4",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 3,
        question:
          "Which of the following devices can be used to produce both transverse and longitudinal waves?",
        answer: "helical spring",
        options: [
          "a spring",
          "ripple tank",
          "helical spring",
          "a tunning fork",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 4,
        question: "Waves transfer",
        answer: "Energy",
        options: ["Energy", "Magnitude", "Frequency", "Velocity"],
      },
      {
        numb: 5,
        question: "Which of the following is a method of energy transfer?",
        answer: "All of these",
        options: ["Conduction", "Radiation", "Wave motion", "All of these"],
      },
    ],
  },
  {
    mcq: [
      {
        numb: 6,
        question: "In a vacuum, all electromagnetic waves have the same",
        answer: "Speed",
        options: ["Speed", "Frequency", "Amplitude", "Wavelength"],
      },
      {
        numb: 7,
        question:
          "A large ripple tank with a vibrator working at a frequency of 30 Hz produces complete waves in a distance of 50 cm. The velocity of the wave is",
        answer: "60 cm s<sup>-1</sup>",
        options: [
          "53 cm s<sup>-1</sup>",
          "60 cm s<sup>-1</sup>",
          "750 cm s<sup>-1</sup>",
          "1500 cm s<sup>-1</sup>",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 8,
        question:
          "Which of the following characteristics of a wave is independent of the others?",
        answer: "Amplitude",
        options: ["Speed", "Frequency", "Amplitude", "Wavelength"],
      },
      {
        numb: 9,
        question: "The relation between v, f and λ of a wave is",
        answer: "fλ=v",
        options: ["vf=λ", "fλ=v", "vλ=f", "v=λ/f"],
      },
      {
        numb: 10,
        question:
          "__ are those waves which require some medium for their propogation",
        answer: "Mechanical waves",
        options: [
          "Mechanical waves",
          "Longitudinal waves",
          "Free waves",
          "Electromagnetic waves",
        ],
      },
    ],
  },
  {
    mcq: [
      {
        numb: 11,
        question:
          "__ is a device used to produce water waves and to demonstrate different properties of water waves like reflection, refraction and diffraction.",
        answer: "Ripple tank",
        options: ["Thermometer", "Ripple tank", "Barometer", "slinky"],
      },
      {
        numb: 12,
        question:
          "The bending of waves around obstacles or sharp edges is called __ of waves.",
        answer: "Difraction",
        options: ["Difraction", "Rarefaction", "turning", "Reflection"],
      },
      {
        numb: 13,
        question:
          "When waves from one medium enter the second medium at some angle their direction of travel may change. This phenomenon is called__of waves",
        answer: "Reflection",
        options: ["Difraction", "Rarefaction", "turning", "Reflection"],
      },
      {
        numb: 14,
        question:
          "The maximum displacement from mean position of a body performing SHM is called__.",
        answer: "Amplitude",
        options: ["Speed", "Frequency", "Amplitude", "Wavelength"],
      },
      {
        numb: 15,
        question:
          "The motion of a mass attached to a spring, simple pendulum and that of a ball inside a bowl is__.",
        answer: "SHM",
        options: ["SHM", "Random", "circular", "improper"],
      },
    ],
  },
  {
    mcq: [
      {
        numb: 16,
        question:
          " A human eardrum can oscillate back and forth up to ___ times in one second",
        answer: "20000",
        options: ["20", "200", "20000", "10000"],
      },
      {
        numb: 17,
        question: "the ball and the bowl system have which type of motion?",
        options: ["Rotatory", "circulat", "Random", "SHM"],
        answer: "SHM",
      },
      {
        numb: 18,
        question: "The highest point if a wave is called__?",
        options: ["crest", "troughs", "propogation", "Not-defined"],
        answer: "crest",
      },
      {
        numb: 19,

        question: "the lowest point of a wave us called__?",
        options: ["crest", "troughs", "propogation", "Not-defined"],
        answer: "troughs",
      },
      {
        numb: 20,

        question:
          "The ripple tank is used to define the characteristics if a ____?",
        options: ["water", "wave", "gas", "solid"],
        answer: "wave",
      },
    ],
  },
];
export const ch1mcqs = [
  {
    numb: 1,
    question: "Which of the following is an example of simple harmonic motion?",
    answer: "the motion of simple pendulum",
    options: [
      " the motion of simple pendulum",
      " the motion of ceiling fan",
      " the spinning of the Earth on its axis",
      "a bouncing ball on a floor",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 2,
    question:
      "If the mass of the bob of a pendulum is increased by a factor of 3, the period of the pendulum's motion will",
    answer: "remain the same ",
    options: [
      "be increased by a factor of 2 ",
      " remain the same ",
      " be decreased by a factor of 2 ",
      " be decreased by a factor of 4",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 3,
    question:
      "Which of the following devices can be used to produce both transverse and longitudinal waves?",
    answer: "helical spring",
    options: ["a spring", "ripple tank", "helical spring", "a tunning fork"],
  },
  {
    numb: 4,
    question: "Waves transfer",
    answer: "Energy",
    options: ["Energy", "Magnitude", "Frequency", "Velocity"],
  },
  {
    numb: 5,
    question: "Which of the following is a method of energy transfer?",
    answer: "All of these",
    options: ["Conduction", "Radiation", "Wave motion", "All of these"],
  },
  {
    numb: 6,
    question: "In a vacuum, all electromagnetic waves have the same",
    answer: "Speed",
    options: ["Speed", "Frequency", "Amplitude", "Wavelength"],
  },
  {
    numb: 7,
    question:
      "A large ripple tank with a vibrator working at a frequency of 30 Hz produces complete waves in a distance of 50 cm. The velocity of the wave is",
    answer: "60 cm s<sup>-1</sup>",
    options: [
      "53 cm s<sup>-1</sup>",
      "60 cm s<sup>-1</sup>",
      "750 cm s<sup>-1</sup>",
      "1500 cm s<sup>-1</sup>",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 8,
    question:
      "Which of the following characteristics of a wave is independent of the others?",
    answer: "Amplitude",
    options: ["Speed", "Frequency", "Amplitude", "Wavelength"],
  },
  {
    numb: 9,
    question: "The relation between v, f and λ of a wave is",
    answer: "fλ=v",
    options: ["vf=λ", "fλ=v", "vλ=f", "v=λ/f"],
  },
  {
    numb: 10,
    question:
      "__ are those waves which require some medium for their propogation",
    answer: "Mechanical waves",
    options: [
      "Mechanical waves",
      "Longitudinal waves",
      "Free waves",
      "Electromagnetic waves",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 11,
    question:
      "__ is a device used to produce water waves and to demonstrate different properties of water waves like reflection, refraction and diffraction.",
    answer: "Ripple tank",
    options: ["Thermometer", "Ripple tank", "Barometer", "slinky"],
  },
  {
    numb: 12,
    question:
      "The bending of waves around obstacles or sharp edges is called __ of waves.",
    answer: "Difraction",
    options: ["Difraction", "Rarefaction", "turning", "Reflection"],
  },
  {
    numb: 13,
    question:
      "When waves from one medium enter the second medium at some angle their direction of travel may change. This phenomenon is called__of waves",
    answer: "Reflection",
    options: ["Difraction", "Rarefaction", "turning", "Reflection"],
  },
  {
    numb: 14,
    question:
      "The maximum displacement from mean position of a body performing SHM is called__.",
    answer: "Amplitude",
    options: ["Speed", "Frequency", "Amplitude", "Wavelength"],
  },
  {
    numb: 15,
    question:
      "The motion of a mass attached to a spring, simple pendulum and that of a ball inside a bowl is__.",
    answer: "SHM",
    options: ["SHM", "Random", "circular", "improper"],
  },
  {
    numb: 16,
    question:
      " A human eardrum can oscillate back and forth up to ___ times in one second",
    answer: "20000",
    options: ["20", "200", "20000", "10000"],
  },
  {
    numb: 17,
    question: "the ball and the bowl system have which type of motion?",
    options: ["Rotatory", "circulat", "Random", "SHM"],
    answer: "SHM",
  },
  {
    numb: 18,
    question: "The highest point if a wave is called__?",
    options: ["crest", "troughs", "propogation", "Not-defined"],
    answer: "crest",
  },
  {
    numb: 19,

    question: "the lowest point of a wave us called__?",
    options: ["crest", "troughs", "propogation", "Not-defined"],
    answer: "troughs",
  },
  {
    numb: 20,

    question:
      "The ripple tank is used to define the characteristics if a ____?",
    options: ["water", "wave", "gas", "solid"],
    answer: "wave",
  },
];

export const ch2 = [
  {
    mcq: [
      {
        numb: 1,
        question: "Which is an example of a longitudinal wave?",
        answer: "sound wave",
        options: ["sound wave", "light wave", "radiowave", "water wave"],
      },
      {
        numb: 2,
        question: "How does sound travel from its source to your ear?",
        answer: "by changes in air pressure",
        options: [
          "by changes in air pressure",
          "by electromagnetic wave",
          "by infrared waves",
          "by vibrations in string",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 3,
        question: "Which form of energy is sound?",
        answer: "Mechincal",
        options: ["Mechincal", "Thermal", "Kinetic", "Chemical"],
      },
      {
        numb: 4,
        question:
          "Astronauts in space need to communicate with each other by radio links because",
        answer: "sound waves travel very fast in space",
        options: [
          "sound waves travel very slowly in space",
          "sound waves travel very fast in space",
          "sound waves cannot travel in space",
          "sound waves have low frequency in space",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 5,
        question: "The loudness of a sound is most closely related to its",
        answer: "amplitude",
        options: ["frequency", "period", "wavelength", "amplitude"],
      },
    ],
  },
  {
    mcq: [
      {
        numb: 6,
        question:
          "For a normal person, audible frequency range for sound wave lies between",
        answer: "20 Hz and 20 kHz",
        options: [
          "10 Hz and 10 kHz",
          "20 Hz and 20 kHz",
          "25 Hz and 25 kHz",
          "30 Hz and 30 kHz",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 7,
        question: "Sound is produced by a __",
        answer: "Vibrating body",
        options: [
          "Non vibrating body",
          "Vibrating body",
          "A body in rest",
          " None of above",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 8,
        question:
          "__ is a feature of sound by which a loud and a faint sound can be distinguished.",
        answer: "Loudness",
        options: ["Loudness", "Pitch", "Quantity", "Quality"],
      },
      {
        numb: 9,
        question:
          "__ of the sound is the characteristics of sound by which a shrill sound can be distinguished from a grave one. ",
        answer: "Pitch",
        options: ["Loudness", "Pitch", "Quantity", "Quality"],
      },
      {
        numb: 10,
        question:
          "The sounds with jarring effect on our ears are called noise and the sounds having pleasant effect on our ears are called __",
        answer: "musical sounds",
        options: [
          "musical sounds",
          "boring sound",
          "machinery sound",
          "non-musical sound",
        ],
      },
    ],
  },
  {
    mcq: [
      {
        numb: 11,
        question:
          "The technique or method used to absorb undesirable sound energy by soft and porous surfaces is called  ",
        answer: "acoustic protection",
        options: [
          "Noise protection",
          "acoustic protection",
          "air protection",
          "water protection",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 12,
        question:
          "Noise pollution can be reduced to acceptable level by replacing __",
        answer: "acoustic protection",
        options: ["Water", "Air", "acoustic protection", "noise"],
      },
      {
        numb: 13,
        question:
          "Sound waves of frequency higher than 20, 000 Hz are called ultrasound while sound waves of frequency lower than 20 Hz are called __",
        answer: "ultrasound",
        options: ["gaama waves", "x-rays", "ultrasound", " infrasound."],
      },
      {
        numb: 14,
        question:
          "Ultrasound is also used to locate underwater depths or for locating objects lying deep on the ocean floor. The technique is called__",
        answer: "SONAR",
        options: ["Waves", "SONAR", "Mechinal way", "Non mechanical way"],
      },
      {
        numb: 15,
        question: "The speed of gases in air at 25 degree?",
        answer: "346 m/s",
        options: ["200 m/s", "300 m/s", "346 m/s", "4000 m/s"],
      },
    ],
  },
  {
    mcq: [
      {
        numb: 16,
        question:
          "Doctors use __ for the transmission of the waves of the patient for their chest?",
        options: ["Stetchoscope", "Thermometer", "vibrator", "Barometer"],
        answer: "Stetchoscope",
      },
      {
        numb: 17,

        question: "speed of sound in aluminum is __?",
        options: ["6420", "5000", "4000", "3570"],
        answer: "6420",
      },
      {
        numb: 18,

        question: "Speed of sound in steel is __?",
        options: ["4700", "6807", "5960", "400"],
        answer: "5960",
      },
      {
        numb: 19,

        question:
          "The speed of sound in air was first accurately measured in__",
        options: ["1609", "1738", "1856", "1700"],
        answer: "1738",
      },
      {
        numb: 20,

        question:
          "The level of noise recommended in most countries is usually __ dB",
        options: ["90-95", "85-90", "80-85", "70-75"],
        answer: "85-90",
      },
    ],
  },
];
export const ch2mcqs = [
  {
    numb: 1,
    question: "Which is an example of a longitudinal wave?",
    answer: "sound wave",
    options: ["sound wave", "light wave", "radiowave", "water wave"],
  },
  {
    numb: 2,
    question: "How does sound travel from its source to your ear?",
    answer: "by changes in air pressure",
    options: [
      "by changes in air pressure",
      "by electromagnetic wave",
      "by infrared waves",
      "by vibrations in string",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 3,
    question: "Which form of energy is sound?",
    answer: "Mechincal",
    options: ["Mechincal", "Thermal", "Kinetic", "Chemical"],
  },
  {
    numb: 4,
    question:
      "Astronauts in space need to communicate with each other by radio links because",
    answer: "sound waves travel very fast in space",
    options: [
      "sound waves travel very slowly in space",
      "sound waves travel very fast in space",
      "sound waves cannot travel in space",
      "sound waves have low frequency in space",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 5,
    question: "The loudness of a sound is most closely related to its",
    answer: "amplitude",
    options: ["frequency", "period", "wavelength", "amplitude"],
  },
  {
    numb: 6,
    question:
      "For a normal person, audible frequency range for sound wave lies between",
    answer: "20 Hz and 20 kHz",
    options: [
      "10 Hz and 10 kHz",
      "20 Hz and 20 kHz",
      "25 Hz and 25 kHz",
      "30 Hz and 30 kHz",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 7,
    question: "Sound is produced by a__.",
    answer: "Vibrating body",
    options: [
      "Non vibrating body",
      "Vibrating body",
      "A body in rest",
      " None of above",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 8,
    question:
      "__is a feature of sound by which a loud and a faint sound can be distinguished.",
    answer: "Loudness",
    options: ["Loudness", "Pitch", "Quantity", "Quality"],
  },
  {
    numb: 9,
    question:
      "__of the sound is the characteristics of sound by which a shrill sound can be distinguished from a grave one. ",
    answer: "Pitch",
    options: ["Loudness", "Pitch", "Quantity", "Quality"],
  },
  {
    numb: 10,
    question:
      "The sounds with jarring effect on our ears are called noise and the sounds having pleasant effect on our ears are called__.",
    answer: "musical sounds",
    options: [
      "musical sounds",
      "boring sound",
      "machinery sound",
      "non-musical sound",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 11,
    question:
      "The technique or method used to absorb undesirable sound energy by soft and porous surfaces is called  ",
    answer: "acoustic protection",
    options: [
      "Noise protection",
      "acoustic protection",
      "air protection",
      "water protection",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 12,
    question:
      "Noise pollution can be reduced to acceptable level by replacing the__.",
    answer: "acoustic protection",
    options: ["Water", "Air", "acoustic protection", "noise"],
  },
  {
    numb: 13,
    question:
      "Sound waves of frequency higher than 20, 000 Hz are called ultrasound while sound waves of frequency lower than 20 Hz are called__.",
    answer: "ultrasound",
    options: ["gaama waves", "x-rays", "ultrasound", " infrasound."],
  },
  {
    numb: 14,
    question:
      "Ultrasound is also used to locate underwater depths or for locating objects lying deep on the ocean floor. The technique is called__.",
    answer: "SONAR",
    options: ["Waves", "SONAR", "Mechinal way", "Non mechanical way"],
  },
  {
    numb: 15,
    question: "The speed of gases in air at 25 degree?",
    answer: "346 m/s",
    options: ["200 m/s", "300 m/s", "346 m/s", "4000 m/s"],
  },
  {
    numb: 16,
    question:
      "Doctors use __ for the transmission of the waves of the patient for their chest?",
    options: ["Stetchoscope", "Thermometer", "vibrator", "Barometer"],
    answer: "Stetchoscope",
  },
  {
    numb: 17,

    question: "speed of sound in aluminum is __?",
    options: ["6420", "5000", "4000", "3570"],
    answer: "6420",
  },
  {
    numb: 18,

    question: "Speed of sound in steel is __?",
    options: ["4700", "6807", "5960", "400"],
    answer: "5960",
  },
  {
    numb: 19,

    question: "The speed of sound in air was first accurately measured in __",
    options: ["1609", "1738", "1856", "1700"],
    answer: "1738",
  },
  {
    numb: 20,

    question:
      "The level of noise recommended in most countries is usually __ dB",
    options: ["90-95", "85-90", "80-85", "70-75"],
    answer: "85-90",
  },
];

export const ch3 = [
  {
    mcq: [
      {
        numb: 1,
        question:
          "Which of the following quantity is not changed during refraction of light?",
        answer: "its frequency",
        options: [
          "its direction",
          "its speed",
          "its frequency",
          "its wavelength",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 2,
        question:
          "A converging mirror with a radius of 20 cm creates a real image 30 cm from the mirror. What is the object distance?",
        answer: "-7.5 cm",
        options: ["-5.0 cm", "-7.5 cm", "-15 cm", "-20 cm"],
      },
      {
        numb: 3,
        question:
          "An object is placed at the centre of curvature of a concave mirror. The image produced by the mirror is located",
        answer: "at the centre of curvature",
        options: [
          "out beyond the centre of curvature",
          "at the centre of curvature.",
          "between the centre of curvature and the focal point",
          "at the focal point",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 4,
        question:
          "An object is 14 cm in front of a convex mirror. The image is 5.8 cm behind the mirror. What is the focal length of the mirror?",
        answer: "-9.9 cm",
        options: ["-4.1 cm", "-8.2 cm", "-9.9 cm", "-20 cm"],
      },
      {
        numb: 5,
        question: "The index of refraction depends on",
        answer: "the speed of light",
        options: [
          "the focal length",
          "the speed of light",
          "the image distance",
          "the object distace",
        ],
      },
    ],
  },
  {
    mcq: [
      {
        numb: 6,
        question:
          "Which type of image is formed by a concave lens on a screen?",
        answer: "upright and virtual",
        options: [
          "inverted and real",
          "inverted and virtual",
          "upright and real",
          "upright and virtual",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 7,
        question:
          "Which type of image is produced by the converging lens of human eye if it views a distant object?",
        answer: "real, inverted, diminished",
        options: [
          "real, erect, same size",
          "real, inverted, diminished",
          "virtual, erect, diminished",
          "virtual, inverted, magnified",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 8,
        question: "Image formed by a camera is",
        answer: "real, inverted, and diminished",
        options: [
          "real, inverted, and diminished",
          "virtual, upright and diminished",
          "virtual, upright and magnified",
          "real, inverted and magnified",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 9,
        question:
          "If a ray of light in glass is incident on an air surface at an angle greater than the critical angle, the ray will",
        answer: "partially refract and partially reflect",
        options: [
          "refract only",
          "reflect only",
          "partially refract and partially reflect",
          "diffract only",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 10,
        question:
          "The critical angle for a beam of light passing from water into air is 48.8 degrees. This means that all light rays with an angle of incidence greater than this angle will be",
        answer: "totally reflected",
        options: [
          "absorbed",
          "totally reflected",
          "partially reflected and partially transmitted",
          "totally transmitted",
        ],
      },
    ],
  },
  {
    mcq: [
      {
        numb: 11,
        question: "Hoe many laws are there of reflection?",
        answer: "two",
        options: ["three", "two", "four", "one"],
      },
      {
        numb: 12,
        question:
          "The bending of light from its straight path as it passes from one medium into another is called__",
        answer: "Refraction",
        options: ["Reflection", "Refraction", "Diffraction", "None of above"],
      },
      {
        numb: 13,
        question:
          "The angle of incidence for which the angle of refraction becomes 90 is called __ angle",
        answer: "Critical angle",
        options: [
          "Right angle",
          "Obtuse angle",
          "Critical angle",
          "Straight angle",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 14,
        question:
          "A simple microscope, also known as a __, is a convex lens which is used to produce magnified images of small objects.",
        answer: "magnifying glass",
        options: [
          "magnifying glass",
          "Telescope",
          "Oscilloscope",
          "None of above",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 15,
        question:
          "The ability of the eye to change the focal length of its lens so as to form a clear image of an object on its retina is called its power __.",
        answer: " accommodation",
        options: [
          "Fixing",
          "Near sightedness",
          "Far sightedness",
          "accommodation",
        ],
      },
    ],
  },
  {
    mcq: [
      {
        numb: 16,

        question:
          "__ is the line joining centre of curvature and pole of the spherical mirror",
        options: [
          "radius of curvature",
          "principle focus",
          "focal length",
          "principle axis",
        ],
        answer: "principle axis",
      },
      {
        numb: 17,

        question:
          "fish inside the water seems to be at less depth than that of its actual position due to __ of light?",
        options: ["Refraction", "Reflection", "Diffraction", "Rarefaction"],
        answer: "Refraction",
      },
      {
        numb: 18,

        question: "The refractive index of ice is ",
        options: ["1.31", "1.33", "2.0", "1.5"],
        answer: "1.31",
      },
      {
        numb: 19,
        question: "The refractive index of water is ?",
        options: ["1.31", "1.32", "1.70", "1.33"],
        answer: "1.33",
      },
      {
        numb: 20,

        question:
          "A __ is any transparent material having two surfaces, of which at least one is curved. ",
        options: ["mirror", "lens", "prism", "none of above"],
        answer: "lens",
      },
    ],
  },
];
export const ch3mcqs = [
  {
    numb: 1,
    question:
      "Which of the following quantity is not changed during refraction of light?",
    answer: "its frequency",
    options: ["its direction", "its speed", "its frequency", "its wavelength"],
  },
  {
    numb: 2,
    question:
      "A converging mirror with a radius of 20 cm creates a real image 30 cm from the mirror. What is the object distance?",
    answer: "-7.5 cm",
    options: ["-5.0 cm", "-7.5 cm", "-15 cm", "-20 cm"],
  },
  {
    numb: 3,
    question:
      "An object is placed at the centre of curvature of a concave mirror. The image produced by the mirror is located",
    answer: "at the centre of curvature",
    options: [
      "out beyond the centre of curvature",
      "at the centre of curvature.",
      "between the centre of curvature and the focal point",
      "at the focal point",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 4,
    question:
      "An object is 14 cm in front of a convex mirror. The image is 5.8 cm behind the mirror. What is the focal length of the mirror?",
    answer: "-9.9 cm",
    options: ["-4.1 cm", "-8.2 cm", "-9.9 cm", "-20 cm"],
  },
  {
    numb: 5,
    question: "The index of refraction depends on",
    answer: "the speed of light",
    options: [
      "the focal length",
      "the speed of light",
      "the image distance",
      "the object distace",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 6,
    question: "Which type of image is formed by a concave lens on a screen?",
    answer: "upright and virtual",
    options: [
      "inverted and real",
      "inverted and virtual",
      "upright and real",
      "upright and virtual",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 7,
    question:
      "Which type of image is produced by the converging lens of human eye if it views a distant object?",
    answer: "real, inverted, diminished",
    options: [
      "real, erect, same size",
      "real, inverted, diminished",
      "virtual, erect, diminished",
      "virtual, inverted, magnified",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 8,
    question: "Image formed by a camera is",
    answer: "real, inverted, and diminished",
    options: [
      "real, inverted, and diminished",
      "virtual, upright and diminished",
      "virtual, upright and magnified",
      "real, inverted and magnified",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 9,
    question:
      "If a ray of light in glass is incident on an air surface at an angle greater than the critical angle, the ray will",
    answer: "partially refract and partially reflect",
    options: [
      "refract only",
      "reflect only",
      "partially refract and partially reflect",
      "diffract only",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 10,
    question:
      "The critical angle for a beam of light passing from water into air is 48.8 degrees. This means that all light rays with an angle of incidence greater than this angle will be",
    answer: "totally reflected",
    options: [
      "absorbed",
      "totally reflected",
      "partially reflected and partially transmitted",
      "totally transmitted",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 11,
    question: "Hoe many laws are there of reflection?",
    answer: "two",
    options: ["three", "two", "four", "one"],
  },
  {
    numb: 12,
    question:
      "The bending of light from its straight path as it passes from one medium into another is called__",
    answer: "Refraction",
    options: ["Reflection", "Refraction", "Diffraction", "None of above"],
  },
  {
    numb: 13,
    question:
      "The angle of incidence for which the angle of refraction becomes 90 is called __ angle",
    answer: "Critical angle",
    options: [
      "Right angle",
      "Obtuse angle",
      "Critical angle",
      "Straight angle",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 14,
    question:
      "A simple microscope, also known as a __, is a convex lens which is used to produce magnified images of small objects.",
    answer: "magnifying glass",
    options: ["magnifying glass", "Telescope", "Oscilloscope", "None of above"],
  },
  {
    numb: 15,
    question:
      "The ability of the eye to change the focal length of its lens so as to form a clear image of an object on its retina is called its power __.",
    answer: " accommodation",
    options: ["Fixing", "Near sightedness", "Far sightedness", "accommodation"],
  },
  {
    numb: 16,

    question:
      "__ is the line joining centre of curvature and pole of the spherical mirror",
    options: [
      "radius of curvature",
      "principle focus",
      "focal length",
      "principle axis",
    ],
    answer: "principle axis",
  },
  {
    numb: 17,

    question:
      "fish inside the water seems to be at less depth than that of its actual position due to __ of light?",
    options: ["Refraction", "Reflection", "Diffraction", "Rarefaction"],
    answer: "Refraction",
  },
  {
    numb: 18,

    question: "The refractive index of ice is ",
    options: ["1.31", "1.33", "2.0", "1.5"],
    answer: "1.31",
  },
  {
    numb: 19,

    question: "The refractive index of water is ?",
    options: ["1.31", "1.32", "1.70", "1.33"],
    answer: "1.33",
  },
  {
    numb: 20,

    question:
      "A __ is any transparent material having two surfaces, of which at least one is curved. ",
    options: ["mirror", "lens", "prism", "none of above"],
    answer: "lens",
  },
];

export const ch4 = [
  {
    mcq: [
      {
        numb: 1,
        question: "A positive electric charge",
        answer: "repels other positive charge",
        options: [
          "attracts other positive charge",
          "repels other positive charge",
          "attracts a neutral charge",
          "repels a neutral charge",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 2,
        question:
          "An object gains excess negative charge after being rubbed against another object, which is:",
        answer: "negatively charged",
        options: [
          "neutral",
          "negatively charged",
          "positively charged",
          "either a, b or c",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 3,
        question:
          " Two uncharged objects A and B are rubbed against each other. When object B is 86 placed near a negatively charged object C, the two objects repel each other. Whichof the following statements is true about object A?",
        answer: "becomes positively charged",
        options: [
          "remains uncharged",
          "becomes positively charged",
          "becomes negatively charged",
          "unpredictable",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 4,
        question:
          "When you rub a plastic rod against your hair several times and put it near some bits of paper, the pieces of papers are attracted towards it. What does this observation indicate?",
        answer: "the rod acquires a positive charge",
        options: [
          "the rod and the paper are oppositely charged",
          "the rod acquires a positive charge",
          "the rod and the paper have the same charges",
          "the rod acquires a negative charge",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 5,
        question:
          "According to Coulomb law, what happens to the attraction of two oppositely charged objects as their distance of separation increases? ",
        answer: "decreases",
        options: [
          "increases",
          "decreases",
          "remains unchanged",
          "cannot be determined",
        ],
      },
    ],
  },
  {
    mcq: [
      {
        numb: 6,
        question: "The Coulomb law is valid for the charges which are",
        answer: "stationary and point charges ",
        options: [
          "moving and point charges",
          "moving and non-point charges",
          "stationary and point charges ",
          "stationary and large size charges",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 7,
        question:
          "A positive and a negative charge are initially 4 cm apart. When they are moved closer together so that they are now only 1 cm apart, the force between them is",
        answer: "16 times larger than before",
        options: [
          "4 times smaller than before",
          "4 times larger than before",
          "8 times larger than before",
          "16 times larger than before",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 8,
        question:
          "Five joules of work is needed to shift 10 C of charge from one place to another. The potential difference between the places is",
        answer: "0.5V",
        options: ["0.5V", "5V", "2V", "10V"],
      },
      {
        numb: 9,
        question:
          "Two small charged spheres are separated by 2 mm. Which of the following would produce the greatest attractive force?",
        answer: "+2q and –2q",
        options: ["+1q and +4q", "–1q and –4q", "+2q and +2q", "+2q and –2q"],
      },
      {
        numb: 10,
        question: "Electric field lines",
        answer: "never cross each other",
        options: [
          "always cross each other",
          "never cross each other",
          "cross each other in the region of strong field",
          "cross each other in the region of weak field",
        ],
      },
    ],
  },
  {
    mcq: [
      {
        numb: 11,
        question: "Capacitance is defined as",
        answer: "Q/V",
        options: ["VC", "Q/V", "QV", "V/Q"],
      },
      {
        numb: 12,
        question:
          "__ is a region of space surrounding a charged body in which a unit positive point charge can experience a force.",
        answer: "Electric field",
        options: [
          "Non-Electric field",
          "potential field",
          "Electric field",
          "Non-potential field",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 13,
        question: "__ is a device which is used to store electric charge",
        answer: "Capacitor",
        options: ["Thermometer", "Resister", "Computer", "Capacitor"],
      },
      {
        numb: 14,
        question:
          "In __,the capacitors are connected side by side i.e., the right plate of one capacitor is connected to the left plate of the next capacitor ",
        answer: "Capacitors in series ",
        options: [
          "Capacitors in series",
          "Capacitors in parallel",
          "Capacitors in circuit",
          "None of above",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 15,
        question:
          " __ is the process of charging a conductor without any contact with the charging body.",
        answer: "Electrostatic induction",
        options: [
          "capacitance",
          "Electric potential",
          "Electrostatic repulsion",
          "Electrostatic induction",
        ],
      },
    ],
  },
];
export const ch4mcqs = [
  {
    numb: 1,
    question: "A positive electric charge",
    answer: "repels other positive charge",
    options: [
      "attracts other positive charge",
      "repels other positive charge",
      "attracts a neutral charge",
      "repels a neutral charge",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 2,
    question:
      "An object gains excess negative charge after being rubbed against another object, which is:",
    answer: "negatively charged",
    options: [
      "neutral",
      "negatively charged",
      "positively charged",
      "either a, b or c",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 3,
    question:
      " Two uncharged objects A and B are rubbed against each other. When object B is 86 placed near a negatively charged object C, the two objects repel each other. Whichof the following statements is true about object A?",
    answer: "becomes positively charged",
    options: [
      "remains uncharged",
      "becomes positively charged",
      "becomes negatively charged",
      "unpredictable",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 4,
    question:
      "When you rub a plastic rod against your hair several times and put it near some bits of paper, the pieces of papers are attracted towards it. What does this observation indicate?",
    answer: "the rod acquires a positive charge",
    options: [
      "the rod and the paper are oppositely charged",
      "the rod acquires a positive charge",
      "the rod and the paper have the same charges",
      "the rod acquires a negative charge",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 5,
    question:
      "According to Coulomb law, what happens to the attraction of two oppositely charged objects as their distance of separation increases? ",
    answer: "decreases",
    options: [
      "increases",
      "decreases",
      "remains unchanged",
      "cannot be determined",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 6,
    question: "The Coulomb law is valid for the charges which are",
    answer: "stationary and point charges ",
    options: [
      "moving and point charges",
      "moving and non-point charges",
      "stationary and point charges ",
      "stationary and large size charges",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 7,
    question:
      "A positive and a negative charge are initially 4 cm apart. When they are moved closer together so that they are now only 1 cm apart, the force between them is",
    answer: "16 times larger than before",
    options: [
      "4 times smaller than before",
      "4 times larger than before",
      "8 times larger than before",
      "16 times larger than before",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 8,
    question:
      "Five joules of work is needed to shift 10 C of charge from one place to another. The potential difference between the places is",
    answer: "0.5V",
    options: ["0.5V", "5V", "2V", "10V"],
  },
  {
    numb: 9,
    question:
      "Two small charged spheres are separated by 2 mm. Which of the following would produce the greatest attractive force?",
    answer: "+2q and –2q",
    options: ["+1q and +4q", "–1q and –4q", "+2q and +2q", "+2q and –2q"],
  },
  {
    numb: 10,
    question: "Electric field lines",
    answer: "never cross each other",
    options: [
      "always cross each other",
      "never cross each other",
      "cross each other in the region of strong field",
      "cross each other in the region of weak field",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 11,
    question: "Capacitance is defined as",
    answer: "Q/V",
    options: ["VC", "Q/V", "QV", "V/Q"],
  },
  {
    numb: 12,
    question:
      "__ is a region of space surrounding a charged body in which a unit positive point charge can experience a force.",
    answer: "Electric field",
    options: [
      "Non-Electric field",
      "potential field",
      "Electric field",
      "Non-potential field",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 13,
    question: "__ is a device which is used to store electric charge",
    answer: "Capacitor",
    options: ["Thermometer", "Resister", "Computer", "Capacitor"],
  },
  {
    numb: 14,
    question:
      "In __,the capacitors are connected side by side i.e., the right plate of one capacitor is connected to the left plate of the next capacitor ",
    answer: "Capacitors in series ",
    options: [
      "Capacitors in series",
      "Capacitors in parallel",
      "Capacitors in circuit",
      "None of above",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 15,
    question:
      " __ is the process of charging a conductor without any contact with the charging body.",
    answer: "Electrostatic induction",
    options: [
      "capacitance",
      "Electric potential",
      "Electrostatic repulsion",
      "Electrostatic induction",
    ],
  },
];

export const ch5 = [
  {
    mcq: [
      {
        numb: 1,
        question: "An electric current in conductors is due to the flow of ",
        answer: "free electrons",
        options: [
          "positive ions",
          "negative ions",
          "positive charges",
          "free electrons",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 2,
        question:
          "What is the voltage across a 6 Ω resistor when 3 A of current passes through it?",
        answer: "",
        options: ["2 V", "9 V", "18 V", "36 V"],
      },
      {
        numb: 3,
        question:
          "What happens to the intensity or the brightness of the lamps connected in series as more and more lamps are added?",
        answer: "",
        options: [
          "increases",
          "decreases",
          "remains the same",
          "cannot be predicted",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 4,
        question:
          "Why should household appliances be connected in parallel with the voltage source?",
        answer: "",
        options: [
          "to increase the resistance of the circuit",
          "to decrease the resistance of the circuit",
          "to provide each appliance the same voltage as the power source",
          "to provide each appliance the same current as the power source",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 5,
        question: "Electric potential and e.m.f",
        answer: "",
        options: [
          "are the same terms",
          "are the different terms",
          "have different units",
          "both (b) and (c)",
        ],
      },
    ],
  },
  {
    mcq: [
      {
        numb: 6,
        question:
          "When we double the voltage in a simple electric circuit, we double the",
        answer: "",
        options: ["current", "power", "resistance", "both (a) and (b)"],
      },
      {
        numb: 7,
        question:
          "If we double both the current and the voltage in a circuit while keeping its resistance constant, the power",
        answer: "",
        options: ["remains unchanged", "halves", "doubles", "quadruples"],
      },
      {
        numb: 8,
        question:
          "What is the power rating of a lamp connected to a 12 V source when it carries 2.5 A?",
        answer: "",
        options: ["4.8 W", "14.5 W", "30 W", "60 W"],
      },
      {
        numb: 9,
        question:
          "The combined resistance of two identical resistors, connected in series is 8 Ω. Their combined resistance in a parallel arrangement will be",
        answer: "",
        options: ["2 Ω", "4 Ω", "8 Ω", "12 Ω"],
      },
      {
        numb: 10,
        question:
          " ___________ is the amount of energy obtained from a source of one kilowatt in one hour. It is equal to 3.6 mega joule.",
        answer: "kilowatt-hour",
        options: [
          "Hexaatt-hour",
          "centiwatt-hour",
          "kilowatt-hour",
          "Megawatt-hour",
        ],
      },
    ],
  },
  {
    mcq: [
      {
        numb: 11,
        question:
          "The current which does not change its direction of flow is known as __________",
        answer: "direct current",
        options: [
          "Heater current",
          "Alternating current",
          "direct current",
          "None of these",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 12,
        question:
          "The time rate of flow of electric charge through any cross section is called electric __________",
        answer: "Current",
        options: ["Voltage", "power", "energy", "Current"],
      },
      {
        numb: 13,
        question: "Ampere is the SI unit of ________.",
        answer: "current",
        options: ["current", "Voltage", "power", "Energy"],
      },
      {
        numb: 14,
        question:
          "________ law states that the current I passing through a conductor is directly proportional to the potential difference V applied across its ends provided the temperature and physical state of the conductor do not change.",
        answer: "Ohm",
        options: ["Charles", "Boyle", "Ohm", "None of these"],
      },
      {
        numb: 15,
        question:
          "Materials in which electrons can freely move so as to pass electricity are called _________ ",
        answer: "conductors",
        options: ["Insulators", "conductors", "Eletrons", "Protons"],
      },
    ],
  },
];

export const ch6 = [
  {
    mcq: [
      {
        numb: 1,
        question: "Which statement is true about the magnetic poles?",
        answer: "a single magnetic pole does not exist",
        options: [
          "unlike poles repel",
          "like poles attract",
          "magnetic poles do not effect each other",
          "a single magnetic pole does not exist",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 2,
        question:
          "What is the direction of the magnetic field lines inside a bar magnet?",
        answer: "from south pole to north pole",
        options: [
          "from north pole to south pole",
          "from south pole to north pole",
          "from side to side",
          "there are no magnetic field lines",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 3,
        question: "The presence of a magnetic field can be detected by a",
        answer: "magnetic compass",
        options: [
          "small mass",
          "stationary positive charge",
          "stationary negative charge",
          "magnetic compass",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 4,
        question:
          "If the current in a wire which is placed perpendicular to a magnetic field increases, the force on the wire",
        answer: "increases",
        options: ["increases", "decreases", "remains the same", "will be zero"],
      },
      {
        numb: 5,
        question: "A D.C motor converts",
        answer: "electrical energy into mechanical energy",
        options: [
          "mechanical energy into electrical energy",
          "mechanical energy into chemical energy",
          "electrical energy into mechanical energy",
          "electrical energy into chemical energy",
        ],
      },
    ],
  },
  {
    mcq: [
      {
        numb: 6,
        question:
          "Which part of a D.C motor reverses the direction of current through the coil every half-cycle?",
        answer: "the commutator",
        options: [
          "the armature",
          "the commutator",
          "the brushes",
          "the slip rings",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 7,
        question:
          "The direction of induced e.m.f. in a circuit is in accordance with conservation of",
        answer: "energy",
        options: ["mass", "charge", "momentum", "energy"],
      },
      {
        numb: 8,
        question: "The step-up transformer",
        answer: "increases the input voltage",
        options: [
          "increases the input current",
          "increases the input voltage",
          "has more turns in the primary",
          "has less turns in the secondary coil",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 9,
        question:
          "__ is an electrical device which is used to increase or decrease the value of an alternating voltage. ",
        answer: "Transformer",
        options: ["DC motor", "Thermometer", "Transformer", "AC genertor"],
      },
      {
        numb: 10,
        question: "A transformer works on the principle of __.",
        answer: "mutual induction",
        options: [
          "Electromagnetic induction",
          "Self induction",
          "mutual induction",
          "None of these",
        ],
      },
    ],
  },
  {
    mcq: [
      {
        numb: 11,
        question:
          "If the change of current in a circuit induces a current in another circuit this phenomenon is known as __",
        answer: "Mutual Induction",
        options: [
          "Electromagnetic induction",
          "Self induction",
          "mutual induction",
          "None of these",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 12,
        question:
          "If the secondary voltage is larger than the primary voltage, the transformer is called a __ transformer",
        answer: "step-up",
        options: ["Step-down", "step-up", "Simple", "None of these"],
      },
      {
        numb: 13,
        question:
          "If the secondary voltage is smaller than the primary voltage, the transformer is called a __ transformer",
        answer: "Step-down",
        options: ["Step-down", "step-up", "Simple", "None of these"],
      },
      {
        numb: 14,
        question:
          "The process of generating an induced current in a circuit by changing the number of magnetic lines of force passing through it is called electromagnetic induction.",
        answer: "",
        options: [
          "Electromagnetic induction",
          "Self induction",
          "mutual induction",
          "None of these",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 15,
        question:
          "The type of temporary magnet, which is created when current flows through a coil, is called an __.",
        answer: "electromagnet",
        options: [
          "Bar magnet",
          "Simple magnet",
          "Non-electromagnet.",
          "electromagnet",
        ],
      },
    ],
  },
];
export const ch6mcqs = [
  {
    numb: 1,
    question: "Which statement is true about the magnetic poles?",
    answer: "a single magnetic pole does not exist",
    options: [
      "unlike poles repel",
      "like poles attract",
      "magnetic poles do not effect each other",
      "a single magnetic pole does not exist",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 2,
    question:
      "What is the direction of the magnetic field lines inside a bar magnet?",
    answer: "from south pole to north pole",
    options: [
      "from north pole to south pole",
      "from south pole to north pole",
      "from side to side",
      "there are no magnetic field lines",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 3,
    question: "The presence of a magnetic field can be detected by a",
    answer: "magnetic compass",
    options: [
      "small mass",
      "stationary positive charge",
      "stationary negative charge",
      "magnetic compass",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 4,
    question:
      "If the current in a wire which is placed perpendicular to a magnetic field increases, the force on the wire",
    answer: "increases",
    options: ["increases", "decreases", "remains the same", "will be zero"],
  },
  {
    numb: 5,
    question: "A D.C motor converts",
    answer: "electrical energy into mechanical energy",
    options: [
      "mechanical energy into electrical energy",
      "mechanical energy into chemical energy",
      "electrical energy into mechanical energy",
      "electrical energy into chemical energy",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 6,
    question:
      "Which part of a D.C motor reverses the direction of current through the coil every half-cycle?",
    answer: "the commutator",
    options: [
      "the armature",
      "the commutator",
      "the brushes",
      "the slip rings",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 7,
    question:
      "The direction of induced e.m.f. in a circuit is in accordance with conservation of",
    answer: "energy",
    options: ["mass", "charge", "momentum", "energy"],
  },
  {
    numb: 8,
    question: "The step-up transformer",
    answer: "increases the input voltage",
    options: [
      "increases the input current",
      "increases the input voltage",
      "has more turns in the primary",
      "has less turns in the secondary coil",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 9,
    question:
      "__ is an electrical device which is used to increase or decrease the value of an alternating voltage. ",
    answer: "Transformer",
    options: ["DC motor", "Thermometer", "Transformer", "AC genertor"],
  },
  {
    numb: 10,
    question: "A transformer works on the principle of __.",
    answer: "mutual induction",
    options: [
      "Electromagnetic induction",
      "Self induction",
      "mutual induction",
      "None of these",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 11,
    question:
      "If the change of current in a circuit induces a current in another circuit this phenomenon is known as __",
    answer: "Mutual Induction",
    options: [
      "Electromagnetic induction",
      "Self induction",
      "mutual induction",
      "None of these",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 12,
    question:
      "If the secondary voltage is larger than the primary voltage, the transformer is called a __ transformer",
    answer: "step-up",
    options: ["Step-down", "step-up", "Simple", "None of these"],
  },
  {
    numb: 13,
    question:
      "If the secondary voltage is smaller than the primary voltage, the transformer is called a __ transformer",
    answer: "Step-down",
    options: ["Step-down", "step-up", "Simple", "None of these"],
  },
  {
    numb: 14,
    question:
      "The process of generating an induced current in a circuit by changing the number of magnetic lines of force passing through it is called electromagnetic induction.",
    answer: "",
    options: [
      "Electromagnetic induction",
      "Self induction",
      "mutual induction",
      "None of these",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 15,
    question:
      "The type of temporary magnet, which is created when current flows through a coil, is called an __.",
    answer: "electromagnet",
    options: [
      "Bar magnet",
      "Simple magnet",
      "Non-electromagnet.",
      "electromagnet",
    ],
  },
];

export const ch7 = [
  {
    mcq: [
      {
        numb: 1,
        question:
          "The process by which electrons are emitted by a hot metal surface is known as",
        answer: "thermionic emission",
        options: [
          "boiling",
          "evaporation",
          "conduction",
          "thermionic emission",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 2,
        question: "The particles emitted from a hot cathode surface are",
        answer: "electrons",
        options: ["positive ions", "negative ions", "protons", "electrons"],
      },
      {
        numb: 3,
        question: "AND gate can be formed by using two",
        answer: "NAND gates",
        options: ["NOT gates", "OR gates", "NOR gates", "NAND gates"],
      },
      {
        numb: 4,
        question: "The output of a two-input NOR gate is 1 when:",
        answer: "both A and B are ‘0’",
        options: [
          <div>A is ‘1’ and B is ‘0’</div>,
          <div>A is ‘0’ and B is ‘1’</div>,
          <div>both A and B are ‘0’</div>,
          <div>both A and B are ‘1’</div>,
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 5,
        question: "If X = A.B, then X is ‘1’ when:",
        answer: "A and B are ‘1’",
        options: [
          <div>A and B are ‘1’</div>,
          <div>A or B is ‘0’</div>,
          <div>A is ‘0’ and B is ‘1’</div>,
          <div>A is ‘1’ and B is ‘0’</div>,
        ],
      },
    ],
  },
  {
    mcq: [
      {
        numb: 6,
        question: "The output of a NAND gate is ‘0’ when",
        answer: "both of its inputs are ‘1’",
        options: [
          <div>both of its inputs are ‘0’</div>,
          <div>both of its inputs are ‘1’</div>,
          <div>any of its inputs is ‘0’</div>,
          <div>any of its inputs is ‘1’</div>,
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 7,
        question:
          "The ___________ are tables which give the values of the inputs and outputs of the basic types of logic gates or combination of such gates.",
        answer: "Truth table",
        options: [
          "Truth table",
          "Electric table",
          "Non-electric table",
          "None of these",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 8,
        question:
          "_____ gates are the circuits which implement the various logic operations",
        answer: "Logic",
        options: ["International", "Non-Logic", "Logic", "None of these"],
      },
      {
        numb: 9,
        question:
          "The branch of electronics which processes the data being provided in the form of analogue quantities is called ___________ electronics.",
        answer: "analogue",
        options: ["Non-digital", "Digital", "non-analogue", "analogue"],
      },
      {
        numb: 10,
        question:
          "The branch of electronics which processes the data being provided in the form of digital quantities is called ___________ electronics",
        answer: "Digital",
        options: ["Non-digital", "Digital", "non-analogue", "analogue"],
      },
    ],
  },
  {
    mcq: [
      {
        numb: 11,
        question:
          "The process of emission of electrons from the surface of hot metal is called ______________.",
        answer: "thermionic emission",
        options: [
          "Electric Emmision",
          "thermionic emission",
          "Non-Electric",
          "None of these",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 12,
        question:
          "The __________ is an instrument which can be used to display the magnitudes of rapidly changing electric current or potential",
        answer: " cathode-ray oscilloscope",
        options: [
          "Electroscope",
          "Thermometer",
          "All of these",
          "cathode-ray oscilloscope",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 13,
        question:
          "__________ is that branch of applied physics which deals with the control of motion of electrons in different devices for various useful purposes",
        answer: "Electronics",
        options: ["Kinematics", "Dynamics", "Electronics", "None of these"],
      },
      {
        numb: 14,
        question: "NOT gate is also called as ________.",
        answer: "Inverter",
        options: ["Inverter", "Diverter", "Converter", "All of these"],
      },
      {
        numb: 15,
        question:
          "An ________is used to investigate the properties of electron beam",
        answer: "electron gun ",
        options: ["Electron", "Neutron", "Proton", "electron gun "],
      },
    ],
  },
];
export const ch7mcqs = [
  {
    numb: 1,
    question:
      "The process by which electrons are emitted by a hot metal surface is known as",
    answer: "thermionic emission",
    options: ["boiling", "evaporation", "conduction", "thermionic emission"],
  },
  {
    numb: 2,
    question: "The particles emitted from a hot cathode surface are",
    answer: "electrons",
    options: ["positive ions", "negative ions", "protons", "electrons"],
  },
  {
    numb: 3,
    question: "AND gate can be formed by using two",
    answer: "NAND gates",
    options: ["NOT gates", "OR gates", "NOR gates", "NAND gates"],
  },
  {
    numb: 4,
    question: "The output of a two-input NOR gate is 1 when:",
    answer: "both A and B are ‘0’",
    options: [
      "A is ‘1’ and B is ‘0’",
      "A is ‘0’ and B is ‘1’",
      "both A and B are ‘0’",
      "both A and B are ‘1’",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 5,
    question: "If X = A.B, then X is ‘1’ when:",
    answer: "A and B are ‘1’",
    options: [
      "A and B are ‘1’",
      "A or B is ‘0’",
      "A is ‘0’ and B is ‘1’",
      "A is ‘1’ and B is ‘0’",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 6,
    question: "The output of a NAND gate is ‘0’ when",
    answer: "both of its inputs are ‘1’",
    options: [
      "both of its inputs are ‘0’",
      "both of its inputs are ‘1’",
      "any of its inputs is ‘0’",
      "any of its inputs is ‘1’",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 7,
    question:
      "The __ are tables which give the values of the inputs and outputs of the basic types of logic gates or combination of such gates.",
    answer: "Truth table",
    options: [
      "Truth table",
      "Electric table",
      "Non-electric table",
      "None of these",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 8,
    question:
      "__ gates are the circuits which implement the various logic operations",
    answer: "Logic",
    options: ["International", "Non-Logic", "Logic", "None of these"],
  },
  {
    numb: 9,
    question:
      "The branch of electronics which processes the data being provided in the form of analogue quantities is called __ electronics.",
    answer: "analogue",
    options: ["Non-digital", "Digital", "non-analogue", "analogue"],
  },
  {
    numb: 10,
    question:
      "The branch of electronics which processes the data being provided in the form of digital quantities is called __ electronics",
    answer: "Digital",
    options: ["Non-digital", "Digital", "non-analogue", "analogue"],
  },
  {
    numb: 11,
    question:
      "The process of emission of electrons from the surface of hot metal is called __.",
    answer: "thermionic emission",
    options: [
      "Electric Emmision",
      "thermionic emission",
      "Non-Electric",
      "None of these",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 12,
    question:
      "The __ is an instrument which can be used to display the magnitudes of rapidly changing electric current or potential",
    answer: " cathode-ray oscilloscope",
    options: [
      "Electroscope",
      "Thermometer",
      "All of these",
      "cathode-ray oscilloscope",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 13,
    question:
      "__ is that branch of applied physics which deals with the control of motion of electrons in different devices for various useful purposes",
    answer: "Electronics",
    options: ["Kinematics", "Dynamics", "Electronics", "None of these"],
  },
  {
    numb: 14,
    question: "NOT gate is also called as __.",
    answer: "Inverter",
    options: ["Inverter", "Diverter", "Converter", "All of these"],
  },
  {
    numb: 15,
    question: "An __is used to investigate the properties of electron beam",
    answer: "electron gun ",
    options: ["Electron", "Neutron", "Proton", "electron gun "],
  },
];

export const ch8 = [
  {
    mcq: [
      {
        numb: 1,
        question: "In computer terminology information means",
        answer: "raw data",
        options: ["any data", "raw data", "processed data", "large data"],
      },
      {
        numb: 2,
        question:
          "Which is the most suitable means of reliable continuous communication between an orbiting satellite and Earth?",
        answer: "microwaves",
        options: ["microwaves", "radiowaves", "sound waves", "any light wave"],
      },
      {
        numb: 3,
        question: "The basic operations performed by a computer are",
        answer: "both A&C",
        options: [
          "arithmetic operations",
          "non-arithmetic operations",
          "logical operations",
          "both A&C",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 4,
        question: "The brain of any computer system is",
        answer: "CPU",
        options: ["monitor", "memory", "CPU", "control unit"],
      },
      {
        numb: 5,
        question: "Which of the following is not processing?",
        answer: "gathering",
        options: ["arranging", "manipulating", "calculating", "gathering"],
      },
    ],
  },
  {
    mcq: [
      {
        numb: 6,
        question:
          "From which of the following we can get information almost about everything",
        answer: "internet",
        options: ["book", "teacher", "computer", "internet"],
      },
      {
        numb: 7,
        question: "What does the term e-mail stand for?",
        answer: "electronic mail",
        options: [
          "emergency mail",
          "electronic mail",
          "extra mail",
          "external mail",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 8,
        question:
          "The scientific method used to store information, to arrange it for proper use and to communicate it to others is called __.",
        answer: "information technology",
        options: [
          "Computer technology",
          "Mobile technology",
          "information technology",
          "None of these",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 9,
        question:
          "The methods and means that are used to communicate information to distant places instantly is called __.",
        answer: "telecommunication",
        options: [
          "telecommunication",
          "Radio communication",
          "Computer communication",
          "All of these",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 10,
        question: "Mobile phone is a sort of radio with __ communication",
        answer: "two-way",
        options: ["One-way", "Three-way", "two-way", "Hexa-way"],
      },
    ],
  },
  {
    mcq: [
      {
        numb: 11,
        question:
          "__ is the means to send the copy of documents from one place to another through telephone lines.",
        answer: "Fax machine",
        options: ["Printer machine", "Fax machine", "Scanner", "PTCL"],
      },
      {
        numb: 12,
        question:
          "__ is an electronic computing machine that is used for adding, subtracting and multiplying.",
        answer: "Computer",
        options: ["Computer", "Abacus", "Printer", "All of these"],
      },
      {
        numb: 13,
        question: "RAM is a __ memory.",
        answer: "Both a and c",
        options: ["Primary", "non-volatile", "Volatile", "Both a and c"],
      },
      {
        numb: 14,
        question: "ROM is a __ memory",
        answer: "non-volatile",
        options: ["Primary", "non-volatile", "Volatile", "Both a and c"],
      },
      {
        numb: 15,
        question:
          "__ is such a use of computer through which we can write a letter, prepare reports and books",
        answer: "Word processing",
        options: [
          "Word manuplating",
          "Word processing",
          "Word collecting",
          "All of these",
        ],
      },
    ],
  },
];
export const ch8mcqs = [
  {
    numb: 1,
    question: "In computer terminology information means",
    answer: "raw data",
    options: ["any data", "raw data", "processed data", "large data"],
  },
  {
    numb: 2,
    question:
      "Which is the most suitable means of reliable continuous communication between an orbiting satellite and Earth?",
    answer: "microwaves",
    options: ["microwaves", "radiowaves", "sound waves", "any light wave"],
  },
  {
    numb: 3,
    question: "The basic operations performed by a computer are",
    answer: "both A&C",
    options: [
      "arithmetic operations",
      "non-arithmetic operations",
      "logical operations",
      "both A&C",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 4,
    question: "The brain of any computer system is",
    answer: "CPU",
    options: ["monitor", "memory", "CPU", "control unit"],
  },
  {
    numb: 5,
    question: "Which of the following is not processing?",
    answer: "gathering",
    options: ["arranging", "manipulating", "calculating", "gathering"],
  },
  {
    numb: 6,
    question:
      "From which of the following we can get information almost about everything",
    answer: "internet",
    options: ["book", "teacher", "computer", "internet"],
  },
  {
    numb: 7,
    question: "What does the term e-mail stand for?",
    answer: "electronic mail",
    options: [
      "emergency mail",
      "electronic mail",
      "extra mail",
      "external mail",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 8,
    question:
      "The scientific method used to store information, to arrange it for proper use and to communicate it to others is called __.",
    answer: "information technology",
    options: [
      "Computer technology",
      "Mobile technology",
      "information technology",
      "None of these",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 9,
    question:
      "The methods and means that are used to communicate information to distant places instantly is called __.",
    answer: "telecommunication",
    options: [
      "telecommunication",
      "Radio communication",
      "Computer communication",
      "All of these",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 10,
    question: "Mobile phone is a sort of radio with __ communication",
    answer: "two-way",
    options: ["One-way", "Three-way", "two-way", "Hexa-way"],
  },
  {
    numb: 11,
    question:
      "__ is the means to send the copy of documents from one place to another through telephone lines.",
    answer: "Fax machine",
    options: ["Printer machine", "Fax machine", "Scanner", "PTCL"],
  },
  {
    numb: 12,
    question:
      "__ is an electronic computing machine that is used for adding, subtracting and multiplying.",
    answer: "Computer",
    options: ["Computer", "Abacus", "Printer", "All of these"],
  },
  {
    numb: 13,
    question: "RAM is a __ memory.",
    answer: "Both a and c",
    options: ["Primary", "non-volatile", "Volatile", "Both a and c"],
  },
  {
    numb: 14,
    question: "ROM is a __ memory",
    answer: "non-volatile",
    options: ["Primary", "non-volatile", "Volatile", "Both a and c"],
  },
  {
    numb: 15,
    question:
      "__ is such a use of computer through which we can write a letter, prepare reports and books",
    answer: "Word processing",
    options: [
      "Word manuplating",
      "Word processing",
      "Word collecting",
      "All of these",
    ],
  },
];

export const ch9 = [
  {
    mcq: [
      {
        numb: 1,
        question: "Isotopes are atoms of same element with different",
        answer: "atomic mass",
        options: [
          "atomic mass",
          "atomic number",
          "number of protons",
          "number of electrons",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 2,
        question:
          "One of the isotopes of uranium is <sub>92</sub>U<sup>238</sup>. The number of neutrons in this isotope is__",
        answer: "146",
        options: ["92", "146", "238", "330"],
      },
      {
        numb: 3,
        question:
          "Which among the following radiations has more penetrating power?",
        answer: "a gamma ray",
        options: [
          "a beta particle",
          "a gamma ray",
          "an alpha particle",
          "all have the same penetrating ability",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 4,
        question:
          "What happens to the atomic number of an element which emits one alpha particle?",
        answer: "decreases by 2",
        options: [
          "increases by 1",
          "stays the same",
          "decreases by 2",
          "decreases by 1",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 5,
        question:
          "The half-life of a certain isotope is 1 day. What is the quantity of the isotope after 2 days?",
        answer: "one-quarter",
        options: ["one-half", "one-quarter", "one-eighth", "none of these"],
      },
    ],
  },
  {
    mcq: [
      {
        numb: 6,
        question:
          "When Uranium (92 protons) ejects a beta particle, how many protons will be in the remaining nucleus?",
        answer: "93 protons",
        options: ["89 protons", "90 protons", "91 protons", "93 protons"],
      },
      {
        numb: 7,
        question: "Release of energy by the Sun is due to",
        answer: "nuclear fusion",
        options: [
          "nuclear fission",
          "nuclear fusion",
          "burning of gases",
          "chemical reaction",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 8,
        question:
          "When a heavy nucleus splits into two lighter nuclei, the process would",
        answer: "release nuclear energy",
        options: [
          "release nuclear energy",
          "absorb nuclear energy",
          "release chemical energy",
          "absorb chemical energy",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 9,
        question: "The reason carbon-dating works is that",
        answer:
          "after a plant or animal dies, it stops taking in fresh carbon-14",
        options: [
          "plants and animals are such strong emitters of carbon-14",
          "after a plant or animal dies, it stops taking in fresh carbon-14",
          "there is so much non-radioactive carbon dioxide in the air",
          "when plants or animals die. they absorb fresh carbon -14",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 10,
        question:
          "The number of protons present inside a nucleus is called the charge number or the __.",
        answer: "atomic number",
        options: [
          "atomic mass",
          "atomic number",
          "mass  number",
          "All of these",
        ],
      },
    ],
  },
  {
    mcq: [
      {
        numb: 11,
        question: "The elements whose atomic number is greater than 82 are __?",
        answer: "unstable",
        options: ["Stable", "very much stable", "Not-defined", "unstable"],
      },
      {
        numb: 12,
        question:
          "When two light nuclei combine to form a heavier nucleus, the process is called __.",
        answer: "nuclear fusion",
        options: [
          "nuclear fission",
          "nuclear fusion",
          "burning of gases",
          "chemical reaction",
        ],
      },
      {
        numb: 13,
        question: "Half-life of hydrogen is __ years.",
        answer: "12.3",
        options: ["2.85 years", "30 years", "12.3", "5730 years"],
      },
      {
        numb: 14,
        question: "Half-life of Carbon is __ years",
        answer: "5730",
        options: ["2.85 years", "30 years", "12.3", "5730 years"],
      },
      {
        numb: 15,
        question: "Half-life of Cobalt is __ years",
        answer: "30 years",
        options: ["2.85 years", "30 years", "12.3", "5730 years"],
      },
    ],
  },
];
export const ch9mcqs = [
  {
    numb: 1,
    question: "Isotopes are atoms of same element with different",
    answer: "atomic mass",
    options: [
      "atomic mass",
      "atomic number",
      "number of protons",
      "number of electrons",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 2,
    question:
      "One of the isotopes of uranium is <sub>92</sub>U<sup>238</sup>. The number of neutrons in this isotope is__",
    answer: "146",
    options: ["92", "146", "238", "330"],
  },
  {
    numb: 3,
    question:
      "Which among the following radiations has more penetrating power?",
    answer: "a gamma ray",
    options: [
      "a beta particle",
      "a gamma ray",
      "an alpha particle",
      "all have the same penetrating ability",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 4,
    question:
      "What happens to the atomic number of an element which emits one alpha particle?",
    answer: "decreases by 2",
    options: [
      "increases by 1",
      "stays the same",
      "decreases by 2",
      "decreases by 1",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 5,
    question:
      "The half-life of a certain isotope is 1 day. What is the quantity of the isotope after 2 days?",
    answer: "one-quarter",
    options: ["one-half", "one-quarter", "one-eighth", "none of these"],
  },
  {
    numb: 6,
    question:
      "When Uranium (92 protons) ejects a beta particle, how many protons will be in the remaining nucleus?",
    answer: "93 protons",
    options: ["89 protons", "90 protons", "91 protons", "93 protons"],
  },
  {
    numb: 7,
    question: "Release of energy by the Sun is due to",
    answer: "nuclear fusion",
    options: [
      "nuclear fission",
      "nuclear fusion",
      "burning of gases",
      "chemical reaction",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 8,
    question:
      "When a heavy nucleus splits into two lighter nuclei, the process would",
    answer: "release nuclear energy",
    options: [
      "release nuclear energy",
      "absorb nuclear energy",
      "release chemical energy",
      "absorb chemical energy",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 9,
    question: "The reason carbon-dating works is that",
    answer: "after a plant or animal dies, it stops taking in fresh carbon-14",
    options: [
      "plants and animals are such strong emitters of carbon-14",
      "after a plant or animal dies, it stops taking in fresh carbon-14",
      "there is so much non-radioactive carbon dioxide in the air",
      "when plants or animals die. they absorb fresh carbon -14",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 10,
    question:
      "The number of protons present inside a nucleus is called the charge number or the __.",
    answer: "atomic number",
    options: ["atomic mass", "atomic number", "mass  number", "All of these"],
  },
  {
    numb: 11,
    question: "The elements whose atomic number is greater than 82 are __?",
    answer: "unstable",
    options: ["Stable", "very much stable", "Not-defined", "unstable"],
  },
  {
    numb: 12,
    question:
      "When two light nuclei combine to form a heavier nucleus, the process is called __.",
    answer: "nuclear fusion",
    options: [
      "nuclear fission",
      "nuclear fusion",
      "burning of gases",
      "chemical reaction",
    ],
  },
  {
    numb: 13,
    question: "Half-life of hydrogen is __ years.",
    answer: "12.3",
    options: ["2.85 years", "30 years", "12.3", "5730 years"],
  },
  {
    numb: 14,
    question: "Half-life of Carbon is __ years",
    answer: "5730",
    options: ["2.85 years", "30 years", "12.3", "5730 years"],
  },
  {
    numb: 15,
    question: "Half-life of Cobalt is __ years",
    answer: "30 years",
    options: ["2.85 years", "30 years", "12.3", "5730 years"],
  },
];
